[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net se radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software welcome to software engineering
radio I'm your host bries sh manut Our
Guest today is Jackson rep Jackson is
the CTO and head of marketing for Harper
DB he has over 25 years of experience
architecting designing and developing
enterprise software he's a founder of
three technology startups and has
consulted with multiple Fortune 500
companies on iot that's internet of
things and digital transformation
initiatives Jackson welcome thank you
very much for having me in today's
session we will talk about distributed
data infrastructure understand what it
is benefits of using it the challenges
which are unique to it we will Deep dive
into the architecture and design
patterns of distributed data
infrastructure and also delve into
security considerations
finally we will look at what one should
consider while transitioning into a
distributed data infrastructure setup so
let's start with the
fundamentals Jackson can you help
explain to our listeners the fundamental
concept of distributed data
infrastructure and why it's important
absolutely there are a few reasons why
one would want to set up one's data
infrastructure in a way that data does
not live in a single location the old
adage was that I want to be more
resilient a data center might go down so
if it does I don't want my entire
application to fail I would like to be
able to route to a different place where
the data is able to be served and my
application can continue to function
that is what we have sort of dealt with
for years and years and there's lots of
rules and Tools around setting up a
distributed data infrastructure mostly
for resilience and that includes things
like Disaster Recovery you know a site
that's very far away that eventually
gets that data I may not access it so it
doesn't need to be particularly fast but
if all of my main office buildings burn
down I still need that data so I need it
to be and exist somewhere more recently
it has been a challenge of scale I.E I
have so many users that are trying to
interact with my data that having a
single database answer those questions
or accept those inserts is not
sufficient or if it is I'm spending a
lot of money to put a terabyte of RAM
and multiple cores in a machine so that
it can perform at a level that is
satisfactory for my users when they're
trying to interact with that data if I
am in many locations obviously I divide
up that user base and the resource
requirements for each node of my data
infrastructure are lower it introduces
other challenges though however the most
recent reason and this is I don't think
it's entirely pandemic driven but before
the pandemic
sub 50 millisecond response times for
apis were not something everybody was
demanding we rarely heard about it high
performance applications absolutely but
for most people it was you know get it
to me within half a second 500
milliseconds and that's fine and when
everybody started working from home
everybody got real impatient for apps
that were slow and the newest reason we
have distributed data infrastructure and
the one that sort of drives my company
and companies like us is the idea of
extremely low latency so not only am I
Distributing the load across multiple
data ingest points or access points for
queries and not only am I resilient and
not only am I protected in case of a
disaster but also I am closer to the
user so I am lowering the latency for
that response or for that insert so it's
really a combination of latency cost
resiliency and ultimately the whole
balance of that is complexity because
obviously we keep adding moving parts to
a system it gets more and more complex
yeah all of that makes sense so
resiliency scale low latency all of that
is very critical and important for you
know any business that's out there on
the net right now but circling back to
the fundamental concept what is data
when we say it's a distributed data
infrastructure what does that mean it
means that I'm going to store data in
more than one place the idea that that I
may divide my data into multiple servers
I may divide my data across multiple
regions I may replicate my data in whole
or in part across multiple regions so
traditional sharding divides up very
large data sets across multiple servers
keeps track of where each piece of data
is and allows you to access it so that's
the basic level of putting data in more
than one place when I talk about
distributed data INF infastructure I
mean your data is accessible in whole or
in part in many different locations
around let's say the globe or it may be
around your service area but distributed
data infrastructure are the servers and
the connections and the software that
allows you to access data as if it was
sitting on your laptop as quickly as
possible even though it may be located
in multiple places in the world
understood and why is it called Data
infrastructure is it same as distributed
databases or when you say it's
distributed data infrastructure are you
taking a different view of what the
stack is and Does it include additional
components and layers well
infrastructure requires obviously
Hardware the servers to run it the
software that is going to store your
data and when you have distributed data
you need some way for those independent
nodes those independent servers to speak
to each other so there's tooling around
around how those nodes communicate how a
transaction that happens on one server
is replicated and reconciled on a
different server where a similar
transaction might have just happened to
affect the exact same record so the
tooling and systems to make sure that
everything in an end state is what
should have happened based on you know
the time at which it happened anywhere
in the world is complex and requires a
lot of individual parts so I refer to
infrastructure as a combination of
software and hardware and not just
databases but all the tooling around it
that allow you to break them out and
have them live more than one place right
so in my mindsight it's much more
comprehensive than just a distributed
database because includes not just the
database But it includes the processing
it includes the engines the integration
tools and all of that is combined under
the umbrella term data distributed data
structure absolutely when you think
about what you're really trying to
achieve extremely low latency for users
that are dispersed around the planet
there's a lot of tooling that not only
goes into just storing the data and
making sure that this entity that covers
the planet has your data and is readily
accessible but there's also a lot of
tooling to make sure that people can
push data in in a way or get data out in
a way that fits with their end use so
there's also lots of software involved
in making it easy we often refer to
distributed data infrastructure as a
data fabric there's a lot of work that
goes into making a weave there's lots of
different sorts of fibers that go into
it but the objective is to provide a
uniform surface from which and to which
you know data can flow understood and
are there any specific considerations
which are required for distributed data
infrastructure to be optimized for iot
applications yes I think one of the of
cited statistics is that we're going to
have several trillion devices you know
generating information and where that
information ends up whether it's just
fired off not collected and it exists in
The Ether and that device just measures
something and every once in a while you
go over and just look at the current
value that's a perfectly good sensor and
walking across the room and looking at
it is a perfectly good way to manage
if I've got several hundred under my
domain or you know several hundred
thousand for say a large manufacturering
concern then really what you're looking
at is how can I handle that level of
throughput how can I handle it securely
how can I reconcile that if they are
doing inest into different nodes
different servers different databases in
different parts of the planet how do I
leave those together how do I make sure
that I Recon recile them in time so are
my clocks aligned things like that
there's a lot of concerns when you're
talking about distributed data
infrastructure that are absolutely table
sticks in order to be able to say I
trust that if somebody in Mumbai puts a
piece of data into this server that
somebody in Los Angeles when they ask
for a question of my server will get the
right answer that includes the data that
was just inserted you know on the other
side of the planet
true we touched on the benefits but I
want to double click on some of the
benefits that you mentioned earlier so
data availability is crucial for
businesses how does Distributing data
across geographical locations on nodes
contribute to improve data availability
and how does that all sync up together
you can imagine and we can go back to
the iot use case when I have hundreds of
thousands of sensors producing data I
may be looking at temperature and I
might be looking at vibration and I
might be looking at any number of
parameters that are coming off that
machine that I'm measuring and if I
ingest that all off of hundreds of
thousands of machine that are creating
that data every five milliseconds that
is a tremendous amount of Ingress and
when I have all of that data the
availability of it depends on what my
use case is if I'm just trying to create
a dashboard that tells me the current
value of you know what's the current
temperature of that machine is it too
hot do I need to turn it off for a while
do I need to increase cooling is it
about to fail do I need to do
preventative maintenance do I need to I
don't know change the oil then that's
easy I could just look at that but if I
wanted to allow intelligence systems to
look at data to look at patterns in that
data say machine learning right AI
looking at every single reading off of
every single sensor attached to every
single machine and also considering
other external factors like the
temperature and humidity in the
environment in each location of my
factory I often call it the rumelian
challenge right I don't know what I
don't know so the safest method often is
to default to collecting absolutely
everything so that what truly needs to
be available for my Enterprise what
truly can make a difference what truly
can improve my performance profitability
resiliency is in there somewhere and we
are very very quickly getting to a place
where distributed data infrastructure is
a tool for very quickly collecting and
returning but also analyzing all of that
data in a way that perhaps humans can't
even do anymore so having a platform
that accesses data when we talk about
availability from a data system you're
often talking about somebody typing in a
SQL query and asking it a question or
you know a customer coming in and
hitting an API endpoint that asks the
question and gets that back even at the
peak volumes of hundreds of thousands of
requests a second for some of the
largest networks in the world that's
fine that's we can do that with existing
infrastructure today but when you talk
about a machine learning algorithm that
needs or is capable of processing things
hundreds of thousands of times faster
than that because what they really want
to do is recognize a pattern and perhaps
turn off a machine before it blows up
and kills people or you know in some
people's eyes even worse loses
productivity for a day you know at a
million dollars an hour that's what
availability is becoming it's not just
what you and I are going to look at and
be able to comprehend it's What machines
are going to look at and the depth and
breadth of what they can look at is
several orders of magnitude obviously
what we can do and that's where the
industry is going so while we say low
latency for users and API endpoints or
ingest from lots of users that are Maybe
adding comments on a YouTube blog that's
really really small scale compared to
what we're seeing in Industry today and
so infrastructure needs to be able to
handle that and that's what we are
building tooling for that's what truly
distributed data infrastructure is great
at do you have any specific examples
where you know any of your customers
have benefited from implementing
distributed data infrastructure I think
it will really help bring those points
around resiliency scalability latency to
life absolutely I worked on an iot
platform in a former life and we were
effectively censorize hot dip
galvanizing plant which is where you
take the steel poles that hold up road
signs like literally everything is hot
tip galvanized in the world so that the
steel doesn't rust and that process was
incredibly manual and the people who dip
each of these massive pieces of metal in
you know three chemical ponds and then
in a pool of molten nickel we're
treating it like it was an art now the
reality is the system required or the
the legal requirements for any given you
know road sign holding piece of metal
have a certain thickness of zinc that
you need to put on there in order to
guarantee that it won't rust and it will
withstand whatever element and whatever
environment it's put in and treating it
like an art didn't seem right because
what humans would do would prefer to
never put too little on so they don't
have to red it and as a result they were
putting way more zinc on this metal than
they needed to and that was the primary
cost center for this business so we
built a system where we could censorize
it and we could say it was in this tank
for this long this tank for this long
this tank for this long then we dipped
it in the zinc and the operator left it
this long then we measured how thick it
was versus how thick it was supposed to
be and we said we're going to put a
green light right in front of you and I
know you think it's an art when you take
it out but take it out when the green
light is there I promise you we've
already done the work we've analyzed not
only the length of time and the millspec
of how thick that zinc was but we've
also analyzed all the external factors
like weather temperature humidity and
when that light turns green pull it out
of that tank and sure enough we were
meeting the millspec required and we
were using 30% of the raw materials that
we were using before so that's a 70%
increase in efficiency and we did that
project in a few weeks because humans
are really terrible at judging
objectively chemical processes that
science and measurement and tooling is
much better at and in order to be able
to make that calculation as to when that
light turns green we needed all of the
data from all of the tanks and all of
the external factors and we needed a
system that could also respond and have
output that said hey you're done turn on
the green light and tell that guy to
take that out of that tank as a result
profits jumped and the customer was
extremely happy very interesting example
and help me understand the scale of the
operation which needed a distributed
data infrastructure and a traditional
relational database would not have
worked over year so it needed to be able
to store the data locally because the
other thing that's extremely true about
hot dip galvanizing is it's an
incredibly dirty process and it doesn't
happen anywhere where humans are so it
often doesn't happen anywhere where
there's really good network connectivity
and it happens across massive yards so
the measurement of that millspec doesn't
happen next to the shed but the shed
usually isn't super close to the office
either in case there's an industrial
accident so there's lots of failures in
network connectivity so you need to work
locally so you need to be able to store
that somewhere and then when network
connectivity is restored which it does
sporadically you need to be able to move
move that data into the central location
because looking at it locally only gives
me you know one two maybe a hundred
pieces a day but I need enough data to
tell you exactly what environmental
factors exactly what temperatures each
of the tanks are at to be able to build
an algorithm that will tell me to take
it out at the right time no matter where
I am across the country so in essence
what we did is we were recording the
data locally
we were employing an algorithm that
ultimately told you to turn the light on
but the algorithm was a product of all
of the aggregate data across all of the
individual facilities where this process
was happening right understood so I
guess this is an example of known
unknowns being translated into known
knowns and then having an implementation
which you know analyzed it and changed
an art form into a highly mechanical
form absolutely that's exactly it we
took raw data and we turned it into
Human Action excellent let's move on to
the challenges so what are some of the
challenges that organizations pH or
might face when implementing a
distributed data infrastructure and if
you've got an example to walk us through
those challenges that any of your
clients have faced or you know while you
have been consulting or in your current
role where you have experienced clients
implementing or distributed data
infrastructure what were the challenges
they fa that would help bring it to life
as well it's a great question because
the challenges are different every time
and I think one of the things we've
learned at Harper DB as we go into
different organizations to help them
improve performance and resiliency and
all of the benefits is understanding
exactly what their topology right where
their servers should live what their
servers need to accomplish what is the
load and what is the necessity for
availability and ultimately what is the
scale of that data I think most most
Industries most clients have a certain
amount of data that they are used to
dealing with and when you start to tell
them that there are insights right the
the unknown unknowns that they could
capture and optimize from Maybe not
today but in the future the planning of
that topology and that infrastructure
including where I am today and the path
to get to you know the end result that's
the biggest challenge because for most
customers they can't afford to shut down
their entire data infrastructure and
migration feels like a multi-year task
so the opportunity is to provide them an
infrastructure where it's not rip and
replace they don't have to tear things
out they want to extend their existing
system with distributed data
infrastructure that delivers all of the
benefits and the challenges are how do
we keep your existing system functional
as functional as possible possible while
delivering those benefits out on the
edge specifically we talk about you know
the observability is super hot right now
it's the hottest Trend everybody wants
so many statistics about their systems
operating status primarily to optimize
to make sure things don't go wrong
because data infrastructure is so
critical but when we are doing that we
look at what's truly happening in your
data pipeline so for requests say how
many layers of caching are there what is
the response time for every single layer
of that cash what are your cash hit and
Mis rates how can we optimize that we're
working with a specific customer right
now who has 600 million SKS and they are
trying to manage the availability of
those and obviously you don't want to
serve every single one of those from a
database in real time you want to cash
as many of those responses as you can so
how do you cash them how do you decide
what gets cash what remains cash what
gets evicted if I run out of room
because servers do have limitations and
how do I optimize this because it might
not be the same in every location so my
rules for evicting things from a cache
my rules for partitioning data and
moving a record perhaps somewhere else
are wholly determined based on the user
behavior in that particular region so
helping them plan and understand the
moving data is a natural part of a
distributed system as opposed to you
know the current thinking which is my
database lives right over there and
that's where all my data is so getting
customers used to the idea that
sometimes the machine or the system or
the algorithm or the AI is going to make
decisions that maybe your human engineer
wouldn't do and your human engineer will
say I don't know why that record isn't
in cash because I just hit it and it
came back as a cash Miss I just hit it
and it came back with it had to access
disc instead of you know being pulled
from the ram why is that and in many
times we investigate and we're like well
because you're literally the only person
hitting that particular endpoint asking
for that particular item and it's their
favorite item it's the item they always
test with but it has fallen out of favor
because there is a newer model or
everybody else in the world is looking
for a different version now so helping
them understand how the rules are often
optimized not by humans but by machines
and another great example is the idea of
database admins who like to look at
query plans and optimize queries by hand
that is their job that is what they've
been doing for 30 years 40 years so they
know exactly how to do it they work
really really well with Antiquated
databases I won't say Antiquated but
just Enterprise scale databases that
have been running for over a decade and
they know every toggle that they can
handle and it's hard to help them
understand that modern systems can
toggle those things on and off and
reorder and optimize queries far better
far faster and in real time than a human
can do it so helping them understand
that modern software isn't trying to
take their job there's lots of
complexities that comes with a
distributed data infrastructure it's
just how do you help them understand
their new role as a manager of a
distributed data system as opposed to a
database I.E singular datab
administrator right so if I understand
it correctly it's the challenges are
more around changing the Viewpoint of
technologist from the traditional
centralized database to understanding
the complexities around optimization and
Rule based usage which are driven
differently in a distributed data
infrastructure is that right it is it's
also understanding the limits of a
distributed data system and there's a
mathematical theorem called the cap
theorem that says you can have
consistency availability and
partitioning but you can only have two
right the three-legged stool says you
cannot divide your data across multiple
instances and have it be available if
you want it to be exactly the same all
the time I.E consistent so I cannot have
two nodes on opposite sides of the
planet that are always on and ready to
answer questions if I also want the
second I put in data on one side of the
Planet at the very same millisecond or
you know a nanc after I want to ask that
question I want to ask that question on
the other side of the planet and get the
answer reflective of the data you just
put in because it takes time it takes
time for data to move across the planet
in our most optimized systems you know
we've seen 75 milliseconds to replicate
an insert around the planet to a 100
nodes so it's super fast but it's not
instant and that theorem puts
limitations on what truly distributed
infrastructure can do you could either
lock the row which means that it's not
going to be available to everybody while
I am writing it globally and then you
don't have availability you could have a
single database which means I don't have
partitioning or I could accept that I
will be what we call eventually
consistent and again eventually means
perhaps 75 milliseconds but I wouldn't
want to have a banking app where I could
take a dollar out of an account that has
$1 in it and you could do the same thing
on the other side of the planet at the
exact same nanc that feels like a very
bad way to run a bank thanks so so from
a distributed perspective I guess the
primary contention would be around the
availability in the cap theorem yes and
you can choose right they're absolutely
products that let's accept that in a
distributed data system everything is
partitioned because we have more than
one node there are products in the
marketplace cockroach TB is one that
does global rooll blocking and has
Global consistency right they are assd
compliant across the cluster that is a
totally acceptable Paradigm but you
sacrifice performance because not
everybody can write to a row while that
row is locked so as a result you know
performance may be lower but you get
that asset consistency worldwide my
company Harper DB we focus on
availability so we are eventually
consistent we work really hard to make
sure that our paths between nodes are
optimized and we can lower that latency
you know as low as 75 milliseconds or
less between those nodes to reconcile a
transaction but we can't have both right
can you explain to our users what does
eventual consistency mean eventual
consistency means that let's say I have
two nodes one in Los Angeles and one in
London and I'll be writing to a table I
will be asking it questions and that
will be happening in on both servers if
I insert a record a new blog post I put
that in there and consistency would mean
that if somebody in London or somebody
hitting the London server asked for all
of my blog posts they would see all of
my blog posts including the one I just
put in there just literally a nanc ago
it just got committed to dis the
transaction is complete and they say
give me all this blog posts right then
and it will appear and that is
consistency in an asset compliant way
right eventual consistency means that I
will write it but it might not be
immediately available I.E consistent in
London because it takes time for that
data to move over there the way you
achieve consistency or assd compliance
right that consistency on a global scale
is for me to have the London server
basically when I insert the data into
Los Angeles the first thing I do is say
I'm going to change this row or I'm
going to put a new row in you know lock
this this row and don't let anybody read
it because I am going to change it so
they may wait 75 milliseconds so the
database query might be slow right
because it's waiting for that to be done
and ultimately that is the trade-off
that we make so the idea that for a
real-time system which most often is
user Behavior it is sensor data it is
you know lots of analytics that are
coming in is it really super important
is it critical will people lose money if
it's not available the second it's
committed to dis everywhere because if
it is super critical that it's available
everywhere think again banking
transaction yep then really the model is
to either have Global row locking or to
have a single monolithic database that I
write to that of course locks that row
while other people are like piling in on
it even from London but then their
latency is high because where does that
database live if it just lives in Los
Angeles than people on the other side of
the planet have a lesser user experience
or higher latency while they're trying
to access data so we tend to focus at
harperdb on on making it as fast and
performant as possible for inges reads
and we sacrifice consistency in order to
achieve that perfect clearly understood
we'll move on to the next topic which is
around security security is a top
concern when it comes to data and what
are the unique challenges faced in our
distributed data infrastructure setup
from a security perspective
well right off the bat it is very
similar to you know any network but we
can start with the database aspect of it
in that you know the database needs to
be secured in exactly the same way a
normal monolithic database needs to be
secured right all the ports Access
Control you know roles in users and the
ability to determine what people are
allowed to access let's say what
databases or what tables or even in the
case of our product what attributes so
think of it as column level security so
your select star with your role might be
different than my select star my select
star might bring back everything and
yours brings back everything except the
pii the personally identifiable
information so so normal database
considerations as to how people can
access this data and whether or not it's
encrypted on disk and whether or not we
want to do that based on the tradeoff in
in terms of latency because obviously in
order for me to search stuff and return
stuff that's encrypted there's
encryption and decryption and it just
adds to that time so there's lots of
standard database security things that
you need to consider and then in the
distributed data system you also need to
consider the security of the
communication between those instances of
that database so what sort of resiliency
do you have you know what sort of
encryption as the data travels across
right so at the very minimum TLS
sometimes mtls the idea that things need
to be absolutely secure in flight so
that you can't have somebody listening
in the middle and intercepting that data
because obviously it's not sitting in
one place anymore it moves around
constantly so there's the security of
the channel itself the security of
network access to Hardware obviously but
then there's the security of the actual
transmission of those messages and I I
would say less security than Assurance
can I handle a network outage can I
route around it can I handle the fact
that I might have data that I just put
into Los Angeles server that needs to be
in London but somehow that network
connection I cannot peer-to-peer connect
to it so how do I
intelligently understand all the routes
that are available to me understand that
the data needs to get there and publish
it to that server in such a way that it
still gets there that may mean rerouting
it that may mean publishing it to a
different server that then forwards it
on to Los Angeles or to London it may
mean store ing it and retrying it and it
may mean that I want to have an exactly
once delivery I.E I send it and I get an
act back so I know that it's been
received at which point I'm like that
one's taken care of let's move on to the
next one or do I want to am I okay if if
something that gets put into this data
but say a sensor data chunk obviously
acing back for every transfer of data
takes time it slows down the rate of
transmission so if for raw answer data
that I can afford to miss one or two
readings because I'm collecting them
every five milliseconds is okay if
missing some of that is okay then maybe
I just fire and forget maybe I just fire
it off and say I hope it gets there
maybe I fire it off three times figuring
my failure rate is so low that if I fire
it three times at least once it's going
to get there so on the other side how do
I recognize that I've already received
that message and not accept it more than
once because if I don't protect myself
against that then perhaps somebody could
literally spam me and do do me my system
to death so there's lots of rules around
both the database you know storage the
instance itself the communication
between the system and then when you're
looking at a distributed data
infrastructure what you're not actually
doing is saying I'm going to talk to the
Los Angeles server I'm going to talk to
the you know London server you are going
to talk to a single endpoint and you're
going to put data in and you need
intelligent routing to make sure that
that
actually gets into the system so you
know Global dns-based load balancing
security products for dos in front of
that and you know lots of the big
Network you know services that are
traditionally employed in every Network
are super important for distributed
systems because if I'm able to get in in
a way that is malicious you risk not
just taking down one of your databases
which happens to people you know fairly
frequently but you risk taking down a
whole network of servers so you've
already sold in perhaps a solution that
guarantees sub 25 millisecond response
times globally and because your
distributed system has in some way been
compromised not only aren't they getting
the extremely low latency that they are
counting on probably for Downstream
systems that look for data at a certain
rate so that they can make Intelligent
Decisions in real time now the whole
Network's down so now that system is
going to back up and there's going to be
errors everywhere so you know the other
part part of this is what we can control
for is the manag service network that we
set up but we can also extend that data
fabric sometimes on Prem where we don't
control the infrastructure right it's
the network closet down the hall and it
has a massive hard drive and it's where
you're running the really big analytical
queries because it's just faster you
want it inhouse somebody decided that it
was a good idea not to move to the cloud
for this because it would be too slow
right too far away because I need I need
sub millisecond response times so when I
can't control for that how do I
recognize patterns coming from something
outside my managed infrastructure that
are indicative of something that is
wrong or incorrect poorly shaped or even
malevolent right now we'll move into the
take a bit deeper into the architecture
and move to the architecture section I
appreciate you know as you give examples
in this section you might touch on the
product that the harer DB product that
you're currently working with so feel
free to give examp examples from there
as well in terms of how we have solved
problems around architecture in Harper
DB let me start with asking you know we
we know that no SQL databases are
inherently not asset compliant so the
asset which stands for atomicity
consistency isolation and durability and
the usual approach to solve for us for
this is to use multimodel databases can
you start off by explaining what are
multimodel databases multimodel
databases store data in multiple formats
in order to achieve multiple goals so
the idea if your listeners are familiar
with like a row-based versus column
oriented database each has advantages
time series database which has processes
that create Aggregates right I don't
want to run an you know tell me what
happened the average every 15 minutes
across a Time series database so you may
store it in a different way so that you
have very quick access to Aggregates you
may store it in row if you are often
returning you know individual entries
like this is my blog post you may store
it column oriented if you are looking at
things from a analytical perspective
there are lots of ways to store things
and often you store them in multiple
ways based on multiple uses harperdb our
product is a single model database and
we are asset compliant at the node level
we are a nosql solution but we have SQL
semantics on top of it because we find
that lots of customers are super used to
SQL and they want to join things so one
of the challenges with you know one of
the most popular nosql databases is that
you can't do joints you have to pull the
records and do that in code and
ultimately that's far slower so the way
we have attacked you know consistency is
we absolutely are asset compliant at the
node level we just can't in a
distributed system be as compliant
across the network because we need to
lean into the fact that we are extremely
performant we want to accept and return
data as quickly as possible that's that
trade-off for consistency right eventual
consistency allows us to be as a
compliant at that node level but we are
eventually consistent across the cluster
right for listeners who want to learn
more about multimodel databases they can
listen to one of our past episodes which
is episode 353 which goes into depth
about multimodel databases we'll move to
the next section section which is around
businesses wanting to transition to
distributed data infrastructure model
and I appreciate it's specifically
relevant specially relevant for realtime
domains when what are some practical
steps that businesses would want to look
at or what are the best practices to be
kept in mind when you plan a transition
I think one of the biggest things we see
customers concerned with they understand
all of the benefits they have accepted
the idea at least with our product of
eventual consistency obviously the ones
who don't use other products and we
wholeheartedly recommend them but the
biggest thing is the lift involved and
the fear and the entrenched you know
uncertainty and job responsibilities
it's it's really we can architect the
solution it is
institutional you know concern over all
of the things we've talked about so
going through for a large Enterprise
the security audit going through you
know the pen test going through you know
looking at dependencies and software and
running us through the tools of analysis
so can we survive the gauntlet of you
know each Enterprise's individual
security requirements and teams can we
explain the value effectively enough to
the decision makers at a high level and
then also turn around and- explain at
the lowest level to the actual
infrastructure it teams exactly what we
need why we need it what the ports are
what the throughput is when they their
internal tooling needs to fire off an
alert about something that's wrong how
do they understand that there are no
external transactions coming in but the
database is still moving things around
they still see network traffic that
makes them nervous because they're used
to well the the transaction load Peaks
at noon every day and then it goes down
so it's really education is most of my
job is going into organizations helping
them draw it out they get what the graph
looks like they they get what the
schematic looks like they get where the
nodes are they understand why we would
you know Place applications where we
would and why we would partition data
the way we would and why we'd set up
access controls the way we would but
they are nervous understandably about
you know simply jumping off a system
that works and that they continue to
throw money at to vertically scale I.E
add resources to serve you know a
growing user base or a new requirement
for lower latency so they see the
benefits but there's challenges when you
talk about you know moving from my
current application stack which might
have let's say a hundred moving parts
right that's standard we we have tooling
and systems and measurement and and we
can sort of hold those in our mind and
we know every one of the hundred pieces
and we get it but if I want to be in a
hundred places around the planet well
now I'm worried about 10,000 moving
parts and when I talk about the parts
I'm talking about the database but you
know in an application stack you've got
the application layer right maybe it's
your API servers and then you've got
your real-time streaming service your
message cue like a Kafka and if you use
you know like a mongodb traditionally
you'll have a redus cache sitting in
front of it and if I've got all of that
to set up everywhere it becomes a little
daunting because one of the things we do
is we we draw your existing
infrastructure your existing stack and
we say if you want low latency we can
achieve it with all of the parts you
have right now here's what it looks like
there's an awful lot of boxes on this
page and I'll lean into Harper DB
product a little bit is is what we've
done is we realize the distributed
infrastructure is complex and and scary
and so we built an application layer on
top of the database so you can build
your apis you can build your machine
learning class ification or
recommendation engines there you can
even build machine learning models in it
long running processes like collecting
sensor data so your your application
layer is directly on top of the database
so there's not an overthe a call or a
connection or a driver that you need to
use which lowers latency but also lowers
complexity and then the same real-time
streaming mesh Network that connects all
of our nodes is capable of ingesting
kfka streams it's capable of ingesting
mqtt mqtt protocol from you know mobile
devic or mobile apps so we built that in
too sorry what protocol was that mqtt
sorry I'm not aware of it can you help
explain what it is mqtt is a protocol a
pub sub protocol that has its own
specific packet shape but is a pub sub
base model so think a client that wants
to use a little bit less data than
sending a whole you know Json object as
a packet mqt is more efficient and it
has built-in logic around exactly once
delivery or at least once delivery or at
most once delivery okay it's a
communication protocol it's a messaging
protocol and it's one of the many ways
that people try to ingest and egress or
subscribe publish and or subscribe data
into modern systems and you have to
accommodate that so we built within our
streaming engine because our data
replication Paradigm is Pub sub I can
choose to have a table in Los Angeles
publish to a table in London or I could
choose not to so in many ways I don't
have to move the data around all the
time it's not an equal copy everywhere
it's what data needs to be moved and
what data doesn't and we accommodate
that so if you think about like your
traditional message CU your traditional
database your traditional API servers
your traditional inmemory cache like a
redus in front of a mongodb we built all
of that into a single product
specifically because we knew that this
was going to be a complex undertaking
and we wanted to overcome the objections
you know of trying to manage 100,000
moving Parts when we walked into an
Enterprise and said distributed
computing is your future and we're a
database that talks to each other
honestly the reason we built the
application layer on top of Harper DB
was because we had a distributed
database we had you know message CU
moving the messages around and we went
into deployments which were super
focused on low latency our customers API
servers were you know they're in the
cloud somewhere and we're like okay well
we definitely want to be in the same
region and maybe even we'd like to be in
the same availability Zone data center
can we be in the same rack how close can
we get and we realized that we weren't
really in control of latency there was a
gap between you know where the client
connected and where the data lives so we
couldn't guarantee you know an SLA in
terms of latency because how close could
we get so we built a full function
application layer on top of the database
specifically because we wanted to lower
latency it turned out you know the way
we built it with credit to the team the
care we put into the ergonomics and
developer experience it's been very very
easy for our customers to transition
from their existing API or you know
application infrastructure into you know
transition those functions into our
application layer a they do it because
it's it's easy but B it's it because it
lowers latency and certainly when we go
into Enterprise and we're we're selling
them the solution we don't make anybody
do anything so we can start with your
API servers just staying and making
calls out to Harper DB and getting data
just like they do with their existing
database that's super easy but the
migration plan obviously is to
eventually put everything into into a
single platform so that it's much easier
to sort of understand and manage so from
a migration perspective start off with
this security audit and then you know
make sure that you know your entire
dependency graph and a lot of time is
spent on education and if you have a
product which gives you the entire
platform that makes things much easier
absolutely looking ahead what trends or
developments do you see in the space and
how would they shape the organizations
and the way they leverage
data I think the biggest trend is the
idea that we want to build applications
that are so performant that people don't
even notice that you're loading data at
all it is a combination of user
experience through UI and and
prefetching and being really really
intelligent about how you deliver data
no longer just initiating a call and
waiting for it to be assembled and
returned to you but streaming that data
back in chunks that can begin to have
you know an immediate impact on the user
experience while the rest of it fills in
in the background pubsub is huge the
idea that clients now connect
permanently to a given server and they
say I want to know about this and
anytime anything changes in the database
I want you to push it to me I don't want
to pull you I don't want to waste
bandwidth I don't want to waste the
overhead I want to connect once do my
handshake my SSL handshake once and then
I just want to be here and I want
constant real-time updates right it's
getting closer and closer to real time
not just for apps that you know always
sort of were real time but apps that
polling seemed like a perfectly
acceptable strategy three years ago and
now everybody's like oh it's pubs up
that's better and when you do that there
are considerations that have to be taken
in terms of the load that holding open a
socket for every single client you know
brings up and you have to be able to
understand how that affects your
capacity so what even though we are
Distributing the load across multiple
servers the capacity of each server in a
pub subsystem even with persistent
connections on a pub sub when I am say
persisting a query which might have a
user ID in there that means I'm holding
a little bit of RAM on that machine to
look for records that affect my specific
user or my specific query right a
between these two numbers and there
might be 100,00 people connected to the
server
and none of them are asking for data
between the same two numbers so that's a
ram consideration so how many of those
sockets and how much work can I do to
serve that and does that number go down
does it mean I need more servers does it
need to mean I need to add resources to
each server and what is that balance so
it is absolutely an infrastructure and
resource planning and then obviously
that plays directly into things like
kubernetes and containerized
infrastructure where autoscaling happens
and autoscaling for a distributed
database how is that achieved right I
can add a new node automatically but how
do I get the data from you know a
currently performing node into a new
node that I just spun up to handle
additional connections and how do I do
that in a way that responds to a peak in
user behavior that might only last for
15 minutes but it may be 10x what I'm
used to so how do you not fail in a
really dynamic system when the level of
traffic the intensity of those
transactions can change in a split
second and to be honest one of the
solutions that I think everybody is
looking at and you hear this across
every database when you hear their CEO
speak in public is AI is probably GNA
have some role in that right the idea
that I can spin things up and duplicate
it and I can sort of fake it till I make
it and bring records over distributed
querying the idea that yes I have a new
node but I might actually be sourcing
the data else W until such time as the
new node has a complete copy of all the
data it needs to respond to requests
autonomously so there's lots of things
that are really exciting as we go
forward sounds great we have covered a
lot of ground here was there anything
that I missed that you would like to
mention Jackson I think I've said the
word AI in machine learning Lots today
and I can imagine a world where
distributed Data Systems now that have
multiple copies whe whether it's partial
or whole or sharded and are Distributing
queries those sorts of systems are
interesting but I see a scale coming
that is 10x several orders of magnitude
larger than what we have right now
because I've seen classification and
recommendation engines that are so scary
good I've seen AI that is so incredibly
competent because it has near instant
access to every piece of data when it's
training which is an incredibly
expensive process and then local
training or retraining of a model based
on local data so the idea that everybody
is sort of Leaning into AI is amazing
and I'm super interested to see how that
affects you know what data
infrastructure even looks like is it
something completely different than the
product we've built and I'm absolutely
sure that it is and I would challenge
you know everybody who deals with data
infrastructure to look at how data truly
is accessed what are those patterns
what's the human factor but now what is
the machine Factor how do you collect
everything from so many disperate
sources not just the sensors that you
own but all of the other things in the
world including user Behavior server
load whatever it is and sort of
autogenerate a data fabric that is the
sort of thinking we need and if you're
dealing with data infrastructure in any
way right now and it's maybe the more
monolithic architecture begin to think
about how you can optimize the shape of
your data and the shape of your
applications to get ready for that
because because it's coming right if
people want to find out more about what
you're up to where can they go to well
my company is Harper DB and you can find
us online at Harper
db. and we have lots of blogs there I
occasionally write stuff we have lots of
guest authors that come in that do
tutorials and teach people how to build
you know applications inside distributed
systems we have a veler Center that has
all the resources you need to get
started and ultimately lots of templates
for our applications that can help you
bootstrap a distributed system quickly
and easily and that includes using
Harper DB Cloud which is our software as
a service offering so while you can
always install harperdb locally and that
it's a single npm command you can also
like spin up a free instance online
today Jackson thank you for coming on
the show it's been a real pleasure this
is bries amanet for software engineering
radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
c-rnli episodes of SC radio is licensed
under creative comment license
2.5 thanks for
[Music]